A Guide to the Henry Edmundson Letters, 1814-1847
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Henry Edmundson Letters, 1814-1847
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2010-085
0.1 cu. ft. 1 folder
The Henry Edmundson Letters contain nine letters, eight of which were written to Edmundson and one, the earliest of the nine, written by Edmundson in 1814 to General John Preston. The senders of the various letters include William Ballard Preston; Francis H. Smith, superintendent of Virginia Military Institute (V.M.I.); Bernard Peyton; Isaac White; and Joseph Robert Woods.
Edmundson, Henry, Major, 1774-1847
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Henry Edmundson Letters, 1814-1847, were donated to Special Collections in October 2010.
Biographical Information
Henry Edmundson was born in 1774 in Pennsylvania and moved, when quite young to Botetourt County, Virginia with his mother. After marrying Peggy King in 1799, he moved to Montgomery County and purchased land there in 1801. Having quickly built an estate, he served in the Virginia General Assembly, representing Montgomery County on three occasions between 1818 and 1827. He also served as sheriff of Montgomery County in 1842 and 1843. On 30 August 1828, Edmundson, in partnership with Elijah McClanahan, purchased from George Hancock, Jr. the Alleghany Turnpike--a seven-mile long road that ran from the confluence of the north and south forks of the Roanoke River to the top of Alleghany Mountain near Christiansburg, VA--along with two adjacent tracts of land. Edmundson also acquired the estate, "Fotheringay," which would become his residence. McClanahan and Edmundson owned the Turnpike until it was sold to the Southwestern Turnpike Company in 1847. Later that same year, Edmundson died. His son, Henry Alonzo, born on 14 June 1814, served in the U.S. House of Representatives from 1849 to 1861 and as a lieutenant colonel in the Confederate Army.
Scope and Content
The Henry Edmundson Letters contain nine letters, eight of which were written to Edmundson and one, the earliest of the nine, written by Edmundson in 1814 to General John Preston. The senders of the various letters include William Ballard Preston; Francis H. Smith, superintendent of Virginia Military Institute (V.M.I.); Bernard Peyton; Isaac White; and Joseph Robert Woods. One letter, signed simply, "Wade," may indicate John Wade, one of the directors of the Lafayette and Ingles Ferry Turnpike. The subjects of the letters range quite widely, but many have to do with financial matters, including various debts, loans, notes, and Bank of Virginia stock certificates. The letter to General Preston, dated 29 November 1814, refers to Edmundson's task of procuring hogs, perhaps to supply troops. Bernard Peyton's letter to Edmundson of 3 November 1823 is largely about "the progress of our unfortunate business with the Treasury," which refers to the aftermath of John Preston's tenure as Treasurer of Virginia and the disposition of property to satisfy his debt. Francis H. Smith writes to discuss a leave of absence at V.M.I. for Edmundson's son.
Arrangement
The letters in this collection are arranged in chronological order.
Index Terms
Persons:
Edmundson, Henry, Major, 1774-1847; Preston, Francis, 1765-1835; Preston, James Patton, 1774-1843
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1814-1847. (Folder 1)
  - 1. From Major Henry Edmundson, Lynchburg, to General John Preston, Richmond; 29 November 1814.
  - 2. From Robert Joseph Woods, Nashville, to Major H. Edmundson, Lafayette, Montgomery County Court House, Virginia; 29 June 1820.
  - 3. From Robert Joseph Woods, Nashville, to Major H. Edmundson, Montgomery Court House, Virginia; 25 January 1822.
  - 4. From Bernard Peyton, Richmond, to Major H. Edmundson, Lafayette, Montgomery Courth House, Virginia; 3 November 1823.
  - 5. From Isaac White, Richmond, to Henry Edmundson Esq, Blacksburg, Montgomery County; 24 March 1827.
  - 6. From M. Johnson to Major Henery Edmundson, Fotheringay, Montgomery County; 7 November 1832.
  - 7. From Wade to Major H. Edmundson, Fotheringay; 10 February 1841.
  - 8. From Francis H. Smith, V.M.Institute, to Major H. Edmundson, Lafayette, Montgomery County; 9 March 1846.
  - 9. From William Ballard Preston, Richmond, to Major Henry Edmundson, Lafayette, Montgomery County; 7 December 1847.